Arise for Social Justice Records, 1956-2010 (bulk 1985-2010)
Sophia Smith Collection
Arise for Social Justice records
1956-2010
1985-2010
Arise for Social Justice
MS 458
32 boxes (30.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Grassroots advocacy, low-income rights and social justice organization based in Springfield, Mass. The Records provide a detailed record of the activities, decision-making processes, and political foundation of the organization and its work in coalition with regional, state, national, and international groups. Major topics found in the records include criminal justice, economic justice, HIV/AIDS prevention, homelessness, housing, poverty, social justice, and welfare rights. In addition there are resources produced by many other organizations working for social and economic justice.
Arise for Social Justice is a Springfield, Massachusetts-based low-income rights organization founded by a small group of women on public assistance in 1985. It is an organization led by low-income members who believe that "we as poor people have a right to speak for ourselves, and that as we do, we learn how to build political power for ourselves." Its many and varied programs and alliances seek to educate, organize, unite, and empower low-income people to know their rights and stand up for them; to promote involvement in the political process; to promote self-esteem; to educate the community at large to its common interest in social and economic justice; and to educate low-income people to fight oppression in all its manifestations.
The founding members of Arise, Michaelann Bewsee, Cindy Montoya, Hollee Patterson, Karen Rock, Pam Scott, and Terrill Winston, were initially brought together through the Boston-based group Coalition for Basic Human Needs. Montoya and Rock, who lived in Northampton, Massachusetts, soon formed a separate group in that city. The remaining Springfield women were later joined by Terrill's sister Marsha Burnett and Darlene Nellis among others.
Though the members initially conceived of the group as a welfare rights organization "because all of us were recipients," they "soon realized that all people who live below the poverty line are suffering from discrimination, violation of rights, and threats to their survival and that the working poor and recipients were being played off against each other instead of coming together for your common survival." 1 "By the time we wrote our by-laws we had become a low-income rights organization." 2 In the mid-1990s, Arise added a significant element of "anti-oppression work" to its mission.
Initial efforts focused on injustices in the welfare system. Issues listed on the agenda for Arise's first outreach meeting in March 1985 include child support, the "Up to Poverty" campaign and "Other Issues" (including federal budget cuts, sensitivity, information network, employment training and work incentives, child care, and Pell grants). By the second meeting, the members added the issue of Medicaid access.
Arise incorporated as a non-profit organization in 1986. It hired its first director, opened its first office, and became a delegate agency of the Springfield Action Commission, a local anti-poverty agency in 1987. A six- to ten-member Board of Directors oversaw business affairs and property. Committees provided the "strategic thinking" for the organization. The small paid staff worked primarily on financial development, training, and volunteer coordination. Grants sometimes allowed for hiring staff to work on special projects.
Arise has created its own programs and worked on many projects and campaigns in coalition with other groups on a regional, state, and national level. The organization's interests and activities, while varied, are strongly interconnected, with social and economic justice at their core. In most instances Arise has combined work for specific goals, or to provide services which would directly impact its members and the residents of Springfield, while also working to change underlying systems.
At its founding, Arise joined the "Up to Poverty" Campaign, a statewide, grassroots effort led by welfare recipients to create a minimum welfare payment level for families and individuals who relied on Aid to Families with Dependent Children (AFDC) or General Relief (GR) for all or part of their income. The concept was to bring the amount of the grant up to the federal poverty level.
The coalition of over ninety Massachusetts organizations working on the campaign took as its motto, "A right to thrive, not barely survive." They scored an early success when two of the organizations, the Coalition for Basic Human Needs and the Massachusetts Coalition for the Homeless, filed a lawsuit in 1985 that claimed that the low level of grants violated state law. The presiding judge agreed, and in September of 1986, the state issued a report establishing a guaranteed minimum grant. Though the group felt this minimum was still inadequate, this early victory helped launch Arise. By 1988 the Massachusetts coalition had joined with the national "Up and Out of Poverty Now" Campaign.
In 1986 Arise formed support groups called Justice for Parents and Children Under Protective Services and Children and Parent's Advocacy (CAPA) to publicize the difficulties parents confronted in dealing with the Department of Social Services (DSS). They outlined their needs for better information; improved communication; clear protocols, definitions, and policies; translators; and cultural sensitivity. The groups held demonstrations, vigils, and letter-writing and media campaigns. They worked on child custody issues, foster care and adoption issues, false accusations of child abuse, and advocated for the reorganization of DSS and an examination of its practices both in specific cases and in general.
Arise members trained as Citizen Advocates to assist individuals in navigating the legal system, health care infrastructure, and a variety of city, state, and federal offices and departments, such as Veterans Affairs, Public Welfare, Housing Authority, Social Services, and Prisons. The training emphasized knowledge of clients' rights and effective advocacy techniques. Advocates aided clients with welfare system issues, such as food stamps, Medicaid cards, and fair hearings. They also helped with housing issues, evictions and problems with landlords; and other matters, such as divorce, separation, restraining orders, and child support payments; social security; and disability. Arise-trained Citizen Advocates helped Springfield residents to write letters, fill out forms, and would accompany them on visits to various offices.
Arise also helped individuals through referrals to social service and aid agencies such as the Salvation Army, Open Pantry, Love Center, and Gray House for food, shelter, clothing, and other necessities.
Members organized a Speakers Bureau and sought opportunities to share their firsthand knowledge of living in poverty at conferences and meetings, and give testimony at legislative hearings.
Arise also facilitated support groups and workshops for parenting, empowerment, health, stress reduction, and skills building through its Self-Reliance Center (1992-), Homeless Action Center (1987-), and Myles Horton Free School (circa 1994-).
By the late 1980s Arise was also working on homelessness. Arise members served on various city committees and in coalitions working to provide more shelter beds; shelter for different populations (families, battered women); as well as a variety of services, benefits, and facilities to help the homeless find and keep permanent housing.
Arise members served on committees working to develop a Comprehensive Housing Affordability Strategy (CHAS) for Springfield in the early 1990s. The organization constantly explored a wide variety of alternatives, such as community land trusts, limited equity cooperatives, and AIDS housing. It also worked with public housing tenants to form tenant organizations through the Massachusetts Tenants Organization (MTO) and Massachusetts Union of Public Housing Tenants, and served as resources for tenants' rights. The organization advocated for a rent control initiative in Springfield in 1988-89, and to prevent the loss of "at-risk" (or expiring use) subsidized housing.
Beginning in 1992 Arise participated in a collective of non-profit organizations working to rehabilitate the Rainville Hotel at 32 Byers St. in Springfield, as a single-room occupancy (SRO) residence for single, low-income men and women. The collective consisted of Arise, Open Pantry, the Springfield Action Commission, Gandara Mental Health Center, the Housing Allowance Project, the South Middlesex Non-Profit Housing Corp., and the Community Builders. Arise later managed the building which not only provided housing, but a range of social services emphasizing self-help and mutual support. As part of this effort, Arise also established its Self-Reliance Center/Program to be a community-based economic development and homelessness support center for homeless, formerly homeless, and those at-risk of becoming homeless. The program fostered peer support, the development of organizational and leadership skills, and featured a skills exchange.
By 1993 Arise had also established a Hot Meals program for homeless families placed in motels, organized against one of Springfield's most negligent landlords, and registered more than 2,000 new voters.
Arise's involvement with the criminal justice system began when the organization agreed to employ individuals sentenced to do community service work in 1988. The membership has worked on issues related to police brutality, community policing, citizen review of police, criminal offender record information (CORI) regulations, prison conditions, mandatory minimum sentences, political prisoners, youth violence, and the death penalty.
Though access to health care is one of Arise's continuing long-term interests, the group participated especially vigorously in two events in the 1990s--debates related to President Clinton's proposed health care reform plan in 1993-94, and a Massachusetts public policy ballot referendum to establish a single-payer health care system in the state in 1994.
Other campaigns sought to increase the participation of low-income citizens on city-wide boards, and in the political process, especially through a campaign to replace the all at-large seats on City Council with a system including some ward representatives. Arise worked to defeat the Citizens for Limited Taxation ballot initiative in 1990 and participated in an especially extensive effort for voter registration and mobilization in the late 1990s and early 2000s.
Beginning with the People's Quincentenary Celebration in 1992, Arise launched international Solidarity efforts including sending a delegation to Nicaragua in the fall 1996. They established close ties with the New England Central America Network (NECAN) to work on labor rights, environmental degradation, anti-imperialism and militarism, anti-apartheid advocacy.
In the late 1990s Arise joined the Economic Human Rights Campaign of the Kensington Welfare Rights Union of Philadelphia. The Campaign works "to unite the poor across color lines as the leadership base for a broad movement to abolish poverty," taking as its basis "economic human rights as named in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, such as the rights to food, housing, health, education, communication and a living wage job." 3
Arise began work on HIV/AIDS prevention, awareness, and care in the early 1990s. By 1997 they had developed a program, written a grant, and received funding from the Massachusetts Department of Public Health's HIV/AIDS Bureau to establish and run an HIV/AIDS Education and Prevention Program. As with other Arise activities, the Program aimed to provide direct services (such as needle exchange, condom distribution, and health care information) and education aimed at prevention, while also working on larger societal issues. The Program funded establishment of a Sex Worker Outreach Team (SWOT) to promote self-protection among women engaged in, or at risk for being pushed to engage in, sex work in Springfield. SWOT aimed to "develop and share with Arise membership and the wider community a political-economic analysis of sex work and strategies for changing the social and economic conditions which push women into street sex work." The program, under the clinical supervision of Nancy Lyman-Shaver, included monthly individual sessions and group sessions.
In its second year, the group changed its name to Women in Support of Each Other (WISE) "to make ourselves more accessible sounding to women that do not identify with the title sex worker." The group distributed condoms, bleach and water kits, and educational materials. Its long-range goals included improved working conditions for club workers and decriminalization of prostitution, teaching self-advocacy skills, and providing space and resources to help break down barriers between women.
Arise worked with the Springfield Harm Reduction Coalition (ShaRC), the Springfield Users Council and the Springfield Alliance for Needle Exchange (SANE) to attempt implementation of a legal needle exchange program in city of Springfield.
In 2010 Arise listed its key issues and campaigns as economic justice (to make sure people on public assistance get their rights), "digital divide" computer education, free school education to empower individuals, and peace with solidarity and anti-violence work to educate the community about the waging of wars abroad.
As of 2011, Arise and its co-founder Michaelann Bewsee maintain blogs at the following URLs:
Arise for Social Justice blog
Michaelann Bewsee's blog
Notes 1. Grant proposal to the Haymarket Peoples Fund, 30 Dec 1985. 2. From "Excerpts from the Common Grant Application," circa 1996. 3. Mission statement of the Poor Peoples' Economic Human Rights Campaign.
The Arise for Social Justice Records consist of 30.25 linear feet of materials dating from 1956 to 2010. Types of materials include brochures, conference files, correspondence, financial records, flyers, grant proposals and reports, minutes and agendas, speeches, organizations files, photographs, press releases, newsletters and other publications, reports, newspaper clippings, notes, surveys, training materials, subject files, and memorabilia. The bulk of the records date from 1985 to 2000. They provide a remarkably detailed record of the activities, decision-making processes, and political foundation of the organization and its work in coalition with regional, state, national, and international groups. In addition to materials documenting the work of Arise, the records contain a wealth of mailings, newsletters, and other resources produced by wide variety of organizations working for social and economic justice in late twentieth century America. Because Arise also served as an information clearinghouse, the records are rich with resource lists and reference files on a wide variety of subjects compiled to provide background information and serve as source materials for future activities. Major topics found in the records include criminal justice, economic justice, HIV/AIDS prevention, homelessness, housing, poverty, social justice, and welfare rights.
This collection is organized into twenty-five series:
I. ADMINISTRATION
II. FINANCIAL MATERIALS
III. CHILDREN AND YOUTH
IV. CRIMINAL JUSTICE
V. EDUCATION AND TRAINING
VI. THE ELDERLY
VII. ENVIRONMENT AND SOCIAL JUSTICE
VIII. FOOD AND HUNGER
IX. HEALTH CARE
X. HIV/AIDS PREVENTION AND EDUCATION
XI. HOMELESSNESS
XII. HOUSING
XIII. IMMIGRANTS AND REFUGEES
XIV. JOBS AND LABOR
XV. PEACE
XVI. PEER SUPPORT
XVII. POLITICAL PARTICIPATION
XVIII. POVERTY/ECONOMIC JUSTICE
XVIX. RACISM
XX. SOLIDARITY
XXI. SPRINGFIELD AND PIONEER VALLEY
XXII. SUBSTANCE ABUSE
XXIII. VIOLENCE
XXIV. WELFARE
XXV. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
APPENDIX: Acronyms in the Arise Records
AHA Affordable Housing Alliance
ARMS Advocacy for Resources for Modern Survival
CABHN Connecticut Alliance for Basic Human Needs
CAP Community Action Program
CAPA Children and Parents' Advocates (Arise group)
CAPA Coalition Against Police Abuse (Los Angeles group)
CAVDP Coalition Against Violence and the Death Penalty
CBHN Coalition for Basic Human Needs
CSBG Community Services Block Grant (Massachusetts)
CECP Citizens for Effective Community Policing (Springfield)
CHAPA Citizens' Housing and Planning Association, Inc.
CHAS Comprehensive Housing Affordability Strategy
CHisPA Center for Hispanic Policy and Advocacy
CLPHA Council of Large Public Housing Authorities
CMAR Contract Monitoring and Assessment Reports, MA Dept of Public Health
CONAMUP La Coordinadora Nacional del Movimiento Urbano Popular (National Coordinating Committee of the Urban Popular Movement)
CORI Criminal Offender Record Information
CPPAX Citizens for Participation in Political Action
CDBG Community Development Block Grant
CDC Community Development Corporation
CSBG Community Services Block Grant
CSC Commonwealth Service Corps
EOCD Executive Office of Communities and Development
ETS Empty the Shelters, student arm of Kensington Welfare Rights Union
FCCDC Franklin County Community Development Corporation
FEVR Fund for Equal Voting Rights
FORWARD Fighting Oppression Racism Wrongness Advocating Rights Dignity
FRAC Food Research and Action Center
HAC [Arise] Homeless Action Center
HAP Housing Alliance Project, Hamden Hampshire Housing Partnership
HELP Homeless Employment Leadership Project [Arise-Homeless]
HERA Hotline to End Rape and Abuse [Arise]
HOME Coalition Housing Opportunities in Mass. for Everyone
HOUSE Homeless Openly United to Shelter Everyone
ICE Institute for Community Economics
M/A Medicaid Access
MA DPH Massachusetts Department of Public Health
MAHA Massachusetts Affordable Housing Alliance
MAHC Massachusetts Anti-Hunger Coalition
MCADP Mass. Citizens Against the Death Penalty
MHFA Massachusetts Housing Finance Agency
MLAC Massachusetts Legal Assistance Corporation
MSPA Mass. Shelter Providers Association
MTO Massachusetts Tenants Organization
NASNA North American Street Newspaper Association
NECAN New England Central America Network
Nellie Mae New England Education Loan Marketing Assn
NEX Needle Exchange
N-COPA National Coalition for Police Accountability
NICA New England Central America Network
PACE Political Action for Community Empowerment
SAC Springfield Action Commission
SACAP Springfield Area Central America Project
SANE Springfield Alliance for Needle Exchange
SCPPA Springfield Community Partnership and Prevention Alliance
SHA Springfield Housing Authority
SHaRC Statewide Harm Reduction Coalition
SHARE Self-Help and Resource Exchange (also Students Helping Area Reach-Out Efforts; Springfield's Hunger in America Relief Effort)
SPIN Service Providers Information Network (comprehensive AIDS/HIV info resource, Boston)
SPIN Single Parent Interactive Network [in children & youth]
SPUN Springfield Project for a United Neighborhood
SRC/SRP Self-Reliance Center/Self-Reliance Project
SSI Supplemental Security Income
SUC Springfield Users Council
SWOT Sex-Worker Outreach Team
TAFDC Transitional Aid to Families with Dependent Children
TANF Temporary Assistance for Needy Families
TEAM Tax Equity Alliance for Massachusetts
TEOI Tenant Electoral Organizing Initiative [related to MTO's Rent Control Task Force]
UfSEJP Unite for Social [& Economic?] Justice Project
UHCAN Universal Health Care Action Network
UROC Undoing Racism Organizing Committee
WCSJ Women's Campaign for Social Justice
WETAC Welfare, Education, Training Access Coalition
Western MassCOSH Western Mass. Coalition for Occupational Health & Safety
WIC Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women Infants and Children
WISE Women in Support of Each Other
WMLA Western Massachusetts Labor Action
The bulk of the Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, although researchers must sign the "Access Agreement Form" before viewing some restricted records (as noted in container listing).
The Arise for Social Justice Board of Directors began donating the organization's records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2002.
Arise for Social Justice (Springfield, MA) -- History -- Sources; Massachusetts Coalition for the Homeless -- History -- Sources; Up and Out of Poverty Campaign -- History -- Sources; Springfield (Massachusetts) -- History -- Sources; Springfield (Massachusetts) -- Social conditions; Abused women -- Services for -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Feminism -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Homelessness -- Massachusetts -- Springfield; Housing -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Low-income housing -- Springfield (Massachusetts); Public welfare -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Poor women -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Poverty -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Public housing -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Public welfare administration -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Urban renewal -- Springfield (Massachusetts) -- History; Women in community development -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Women in community organization -- History -- Sources; Women -- Housing -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources; Working class women -- Massachusetts -- History -- Sources
See also: oral history with Arise co-founder Michaelann Bewsee is included in the SSC's Voices of Feminism Oral History Project and the Survivors, Inc. Records. Materials on Gray Panthers of Hampden County were transferred to Special Collections and Archives at the University of Massachusetts--Amherst.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION, 1980-2006, undated; 3.75 linear ft.
  This series provides an overview of the history and administrative structure of Arise for Social Justice, its Board of Directors, committees, and staff. The extensive minutes and reports are especially rich in detail about the workings of the organization. Notebooks, notes, and "to-do" lists kept by various Arise members give a good sense of the day-to-day workings of the organization. Events files document planning and arrangements for enrichment and fundraising events sponsored by the organization. Publications include general information brochures and flyers as well as newsletters and publications by the creative writing group. Arizine, the publication of the WISE (Women in Support of Each Other) group, can be found in SERIES X. HIV/AIDS PREVENTION AND EDUCATION.
- SERIES II. FINANCIAL MATERIALS, 1985-2006, undated; 1.25 linear ft.
  This series contains some records of day-to-day financial business and record keeping, but is primarily related to fundraising. Included are general fundraising mailings as well as grant proposals and reports to foundations and other organizations. Grant-related records are a rich source for detailed descriptions of Arise and its programs and also give a sense of the foundations and organizations funding social justice work in the late-twentieth century.
- SERIES III. CHILDREN AND YOUTH, 1983-2003, undated; .5 linear ft.
  Records in this series include extensive materials related to Arise's work to reform the Massachusetts Department of Social Services (DSS) and advocate on behalf of individuals dealing with the Department. There are also records of children's and youth groups within Arise, and advocacy materials related to legislation on a variety of related subjects such as child care and child abuse. Organizations files document Arise's work on strengthening family support mechanisms, preventing teenage pregnancy, and helping to provide employment for youth. Related materials can be found in SERIES IV. CRIMINAL JUSTICE and SERIES XXIII. VIOLENCE.
- SERIES IV. CRIMINAL JUSTICE, 1977-2005, undated; 1.5 linear ft.